Maddy: There are certain barriers that an
organization is likely to run into when
they’re trying to change and innovate and,
in this video, we are going to look at
these and how to go about overcoming them.
Phillip: So, what could these barriers be?
• Maddy: Fear of the unknown
• Phillip: Unclear goals
• Maddy: Lack of leadership
• Phillip: Unwillingness to change
• Maddy: Lack of planning
Phillip: There are some practical ways these
barriers can be overcome and some of these
solutions can be applied to more than one barrier.
So, let’s have a look at
these in a little more detail.
Maddy: Fear of the unknown
Uncertainty and anxiety around change
are very common and should be factored
into any innovations you’re planning.
Although part of the reality of change is that
people will initially feel some discomfort around
it, it’s the uncertainty of what change involves
that can be the real driver behind the fear.
Everyone who is affected by the changes should
understand what those changes are, when they’ll
be applied, and what they’ll mean for them.
You can do this with efficient
and clear communication.
Phillip: Unclear goals
Something that will always make change and
innovation more difficult, is when it isn’t
made clear why the changes are necessary.
Without clearly defined goals,
people may feel like change is being
pursued just for the sake of it.
It is important to make sure that the
goal of all the changes and innovation,
such as increased efficiency, embracing
a new technology, or increasing profits,
is made clear to everyone involved.
This will help them get behind the
change and put all their energy into it.
Again, clear, and effective communication,
like regular meetings and question
and answer sessions can help do this.
Maddy: Lack of leadership
If it isn’t clear who’s in charge of leading
people through the change, or even worse if
no one is actually in charge, there will be
confusion, mistrust, and possibly even chaos.
The nature of the leadership needed will
depend on the nature of the change in question.
You might need a whole dedicated leadership
team if it’s a big, sweeping change that
effects everyone, or, you might just need a
change champion in each team or department.
What’s most important is that everyone knows who
is in charge of the change, so they can act as
a point of contact and a source of reassurance.
Phillip: Unwillingness to change
This can be a difficult barrier to overcome as it
involves winning over peoples’ hearts and minds.
In order to inspire willingness to change,
you need to have already overcome many
of the barriers previously identified.
There should be no uncertainty about
what the change involves, with clearly
defined the goals, and a leadership
structure that is clear to everyone.
You can also help overcome the unwillingness
some people may feel to change by giving them
an avenue to express their worries, such as
through private meetings with a change leader
or through a dedicated channel on the Intranet.
This will mean that they will feel listened to,
and if appropriate, you may even consider giving
them some responsibilities in achieving the
innovation, helping them to feel like they’re
on the inside, not the outside, of the change.
Maddy: Lack of planning
Without some kind of plan, a
change is often doomed to fail.
People won’t know what
they’re doing, when, or why!
The solution to this is simple,
make sure there is a plan.
This should be prepared in advance of the change
and clearly define what will happen at each step.
Phillip: It will need to be flexible enough to
absorb shocks from unexpected occurrences, but
not so flexible that it has no shape or structure.
It should be prepared with input from the
right stakeholders in the organization,
but if the planning involves too many
people, this may make it too complicated.
Maddy: What’s most important is that the plan
accurately describes the innovation, includes a
communications strategy, and clearly identifies
who is responsible for what aspects of the change.